I see in this I think some of the force
that's coming through him is collective
its he is a he is a kind of channel for
things that haven't been said for a
while and that in some sense needed to
be said it's a you know he said he's a
kind of channel of the return of the
repressed in that sense and he has the
articulate potency of a person who is
carrying more than just his personal
thinking he's he's got a kind of
collective psyches archetypal drive that
is informing what what and how he is
saying what he is what do you think
those things are those repressed
archetypal things well well one is to
certainly his his calling upon men to
kind of basically find their strong
center again and take responsibility for
their lives and their actions and to
become disciplined and what what deaf
psychologists would say it would be to
basically integrate the Cenex the the
that the Saturn archetype the archetype
that brings in a capacity for for for
self discipline for a backbone for
that's grounded in tradition I think in
some ways there's there's certain
simplifications that he makes that are
that are problematic and I just gave one
set of them there with masculine
feminine but it's also striking to me
how much he gets simplistically
misunderstood by both sides in the
effort to impose a kind of stereotype on
him which he I mean that famous was it a
BBC or channel 4 interview with the
awful talent human channel for interview
with with Kathy Newman was quite an
example of that where it didn't seem
like she was really
hearing the complexity of what he was
saying and already had a pigeonhole that
she was trying to kind of hammer him
into and he was reacting against I'm I
deeply admire his capacity to engage the
world with a kind of articulate force he
he's about 12 years younger than I am
and I think has just a little bit more
extroverted predisposition
predispositions in him than I do where I
you know I I prefer being a little less
at the focus of even though some of my
my work obviously pushes boundaries I'm
not as eager as he seems to be or he
certainly is capable of handling just a
tremendous amount of like controvert
controversy and the onslaught of
aggressive questioning and so forth and
he and he tends to do well under
aggressive questioning which not not all
of us do I think in general aggressive
questioning can make it more difficult
for the person who's being questioned
and the questioner to to on dig deeper
and unpack a more profound understanding
that might reflect something that
wouldn't have been included had that
dialogue not taken place so but I have
to say I am in real admiration of even
though I don't agree with everything
that Jordan Peterson says it's it's I
really admire his spirit his capacity to
think under pressure and speak to a
number of audiences I think your work
has been very how
full in showing the the the value of
what Jordan Peterson is doing and you
you must also given given your work be
very pleased to see him kind of bringing
young back into the mainstream we're
talking about going in such a
high-profile way yes there there are I
don't know how much that's coming in as
a return of the repressed but it but you
know it's it's interesting young himself
over the last decades seems to be going
through a quite a in elevation within
the culture and when the New York Times
gave that you know 17 pages in the New
York Times Magazine to the publication
of Young's red book about ten years ago
that was pretty much the first positive
thing that the New York Times had
allowed itself to say about young since
the very good obituary that it wrote for
him in 1961 it it got kind of overtaken
by a by you know a kind of you know
narrower Freudian intellectual viewpoint
and then an even anti Freud at a certain
point anti depth I college II generally
and I think the more we're moving into
what I would think of as the deeper and
more mature form of the postmodern and
the more voices that are being allowed
into the cultural conversation the more
young I think is going to be recognized
as not a flawless thinker but a but a
necessary and deep one necessary for us
to to assimilate he he was carrying deep
deep truths that came from a very deep
dive that he took a kind of almost
shamanic descent that spontaneously
happened to him in the nineteen thirteen
to nineteen twenty P Rhea dand he came
out of that with with real
like basically the end that he gave to
the culture the idea that we don't
understand human psychology unless we
understand that psyche is soul and that
there is a spiritual dimension to human
existence and to human fulfillment that
if we do not take account of it
we are mutilating ourselves and we'll
never really be psychologically healthy
or his recognition that we're all
embedded in a larger collective psyche
that is evolving and that is is going
through its own spiritual
transformations and that we're in a kind
of adventure of of consciousness
individually as well as collectively I
think Jung's recognition of in the end
of it on the individual level of how
important the second half of life is and
the turn towards away from external
public achievement and more recognising
that the inner world and finding meaning
and finding a spiritual fulfilment that
is not dependent on youth and a kind of
robust quality of being in the world but
has is connecting with some deeper
sources of archetypal meaning and
purpose that give us a sense of life's
value all these are crucial gifts that
Jung gave us and and I think more and
more people are assimilating